All right. Welcome to
the Micrometeoroid MMOD,
Micrometeoroid and Orbital Debris.
We're going to spend the first part of this talking about
orbital debris, and the second part
talking about
micrometeoroids and some definitions and things like that.
So,
that's where we are. So what did we learn about the plasma
environment last time? First off, we learned what plasma
is, which you probably already knew. Where does it come from?
Mostly the sun. What does it do to spacecraft?
Electrostatic discharges, interferes with
communication, we learned that, especially at lower frequencies,
and distorts navigation data. And then what can we do
about it?
Communicate in the gigahertz range so it passes through the
plasma layers.
Mathematically account for range distortion and time delays.
Grounding, like we talked about last time.
Choose materials with uniform conductivity, and use
plasma collectors. Although we didn't talk a lot about that, that is
something that we can do.
Space debris, however,
we did that to ourselves.
Space pollution, there's really no excuse for it as long
as we have responsible satellite providers out there.
But the problem is everyone's not being responsible about it.
So we have a lot of space debris we have to work around.
So, current events, I've got three of them this
week. We will start
with
Trent
Douglas'.
And here it goes. Please confirm that you can
see and hear this video, Ron and Rachel, since you're
online.
Do you see the video?
I just see the title slide here that says Current Events.
Okay. I will have to
share
that specific video then. That's good to know. All right.
Can you see it now?
Yes.
Okay, good. Excellent. All right.
Here is the first current event.
Hey, everyone. I'm Trent Douglas, and tonight we're going to be talking about
the rising amount of debris in space and how that
increases the collision risks in LEO.
This is based off a news report I was reading that's based on the European Space
Agency's 2026 Space Environment Report.
So I want to start with how much debris is up there.
There's 40,000 tracked objects, that's kind of based on the Space-Track catalog.
But they estimate that there's actually 54,000 objects that are greater than 10
centimeters and trackable. But about a quarter of those aren't currently
tracked. So that's 14,000 objects.
It sounds like a lot, but that's really nothing compared to the 1.2
million estimated fragments that are between one and 10
centimeters that are considered lethal but not trackable
with current technology.
There's about 140 million fragments that are less than one
centimeter, and they're unlikely to cause any catastrophic
failures, but they're still dangerous and still worth noting.
So I kind of want to pick on the 550-kilometer altitude
is, is that's kind of where Starlink likes to sit, and that's where a lot of this
debris,
and just congestion is. On the left, there's a graph here, and that's
basically just the Starlink maneuvers per year over
time. So in 2024 and 2025, they did about 200,000 and
300,000 maneuvers respectively.
I think currently they're doing about a maneuver every
two to three minutes on one of their satellites.
Not for each one, just in total. In 2027, the projection
was that they would be doing a million maneuvers every year.
And just kind of as far as why that is happening, if we look to the right here, at
550 kilometers, the ESA's calculation is showing that debris object
density is approaching the same order of magnitude as active satellite density.
And that doesn't mean that they're basically approaching the exact same number,
but it means they're within 10 times of each other,
which is unprecedented. And so when debris is sparse,
collision avoidance is fairly simple because debris objects typically
follow very predictable patterns. They don't maneuver.
So we know where those are and we kind of maneuver around them.
But now that there's so many more active payloads out there, you're no
longer just maneuvering to avoid collisions with debris.
But you also have to factor in all the active maneuvering
satellites that are in your orbit that are most likely not coordinating their
maneuvers with you. It's a lot harder to maneuver around objects that are also
maneuvering. Another thing I mentioned in the article is there is a
20% increase in collision probability since 2024.
A few reasons for that
is the mega constellation growth is a big one.
So if you throw one thing up in orbit, it's really not increasing the
collision risk to everything else by that much.
But if you throw thousands of things up there, like Starlink is doing,
the conjunction risk will combine, and it actually does
substantially raise the risk of collision in that orbit.
There's also a lot of legacy anti-satellite debris up there,
and it very much depends on how these anti-satellite tests
were done. So the worst one was China's in 2007.
It was done at about 800 kilometers of altitude, and at that
orbit it can take upwards of 100 plus years to
To have that debris fall back down to the Earth.
So there's a lot of debris up there from that test.
And India's done it, Russia's done it, and the US has done it.
I know the US's one in 2008 was done at about 200
kilometers, so there was a lot less fallout from that because
everything de-orbited pretty quickly.
But all that to say, these anti-satellite tests do have lasting effects,
and we should be extremely careful when
we are trying to do these tests. Accidental fragmentations is
another one. So more and more stuff goes up there.
There's just more likelihood that just stuff kind of falls off of satellites
or old defunct payloads have any kind of pressure
issues or explosions or anything like that.
Pieces can just fall off of satellites, and that's what causes those debris
fragments. And in 2024, it looked like there were more than
3,000 newly cataloged debris fragments from
accidents. So the current projections show that the debris density in
LEO is about to double by 2030.
So first I wanted to kind of mention the Kessler threshold and what that is.
So that's basically, it's the density at which collisions generate new
debris faster than natural processes could remove it, and that
just kind of means you can essentially have a cascading effect of collisions.
So if you're in orbit that is past Kessler threshold and
then something breaks up or there's a large amount of debris,
then it can create a cascading effect and that can blow other
things up, and then blow other things up and then before you know it, the orbit's
essentially unusable. A 2025 study found that
the current intact object population is greater than the Kessler threshold for
nearly all altitudes
between 500 to 20,000 kilometers, and that's pretty dangerous.
Let's say Russia wants to destroy a good chunk of the Starlinks
that are at that 550-kilometer altitude.
That could create a very dangerous cascade of
collisions from all that debris and could effectively render that region of
LEO unusable for quite a long period of time.
The consensus within the
ADC says that basically the active debris removal in
LEO is no longer optional for stabilizing congested orbital
regions. So it is something that we really need to do now.
The crash clock, which I think is kind of a cool metric, it
basically calculated that if all satellites were to quit
maneuvering today, like they just lost contact with the ground and couldn't
maneuver anymore, a catastrophic collision would occur within
2.8 to 5.5 days. And that was as of mid-2025.
It's probably even higher now. And in 2018, that number was
121 days. So that kind of shows you how
congested things are even after just seven
years.
So let's talk about kind of what the world thinks of this and where the world is
going with debris removal. So,
kind of on the good side of things, 90% of LEO rocket bodies now
comply with the 25-year de-orbit rule, which is good, and even better,
80% comply with the stricter ESA five-year
rule. And there's more controlled than uncontrolled entries for the first time.
This was in 2024, so it may even be better than that now.
But that basically means that more reentries are basically
actively maneuvered to reenter than just let
gravity take over.
There has been some traction with the ESA's Zero Debris Charter, which
is good.
Even though that is kind of a voluntary thing, it's not really imposed on all
the nations that have things in space, but that is good nonetheless.
ClearSpace did get a contract to conduct the world's first
active debris removal mission. It's a Swiss startup that
just got about $100 million to remove one piece
of orbital debris.
So kind of where we're still missing is that the 25-year
compliance is not enough to reverse population growth in congested
bands. It's quite frankly just too long.
It needs to be shorter. And then we're going to need 95%
disposable compliance for large constellations to prevent a runaway
cascade of
basically collisions if we want to stay under the Kessler threshold.
So basically, 95% of these satellites need to be essentially disposing of
themselves, which is a lot to ask. I don't think we have anything close to
that now. And we need active debris removal at
scale. So like I said, ClearSpace did get a contract for this.
It was $100 million, and they were removing one piece of space
debris. And you think of the thousands and potentially
millions of
debris objects out there. It's kind of a drop in the bucket.
So there's no real market for it yet.
This is kind of more of an emerging field, and we really
need to look into this more. And as a whole, the space community
needs to kind of take it seriously and put more money towards
removing space debris. I went ahead and cited my article here,
and thanks for listening.
Okay.
Let's see, who is next? Ron, you're
next. So let me pull up your slides.
And Ron is presenting live tonight.
Okay. Can you see your slides, Ron?
I can, yeah. I see the title slide. So,
thanks-
Let me put it in...
Oh, you're in PDF. Okay. You're not in PowerPoint.
Right.
All right. Go ahead.
Okay. So, my name is Ron Smetak, and I'm going to be talking specifically
about the Growing space debris
problem that's a result from some of China's
launch policies here. So, next slide, please.
How do I scroll down on this?
It's not letting me scroll down, so let me see what's going on with
this.
Just a minute.
Okay.
It's locked up on me.
Uh-oh.
Yeah, I'm getting this dinging.
I'm going to have to go to Task Manager and shut it down.
Potentially we could have Ron share his screen.
I don't know if he has permission to be able to do that.
Yeah.
I've got a little green Share button here.
Let me try one more time.
Okay.
Let me try ending that task, and if that
still fails,
then we'll go to share.
Okay.
Zoom sometimes just locks up whatever program I'm
in. So I think that is resolved. Okay.
A Rising Threat in LEO. Is that where you were?
Yes. Great, thanks.
Great.
Okay. So again, the subject is
China's growing space debris problem.
So,
start off here by talking about the picture on the right, which when I came across
this was too good not to use. But it doesn't
do a good job of illustrating the problem here, and that is
specifically that China's abandoning used
launch rocket stages in low earth orbit at an
unprecedented and increasing pace.
So from January 2021,
and this should say January 2026, that's a small typo there.
China abandoned 51 spent rocket bodies above
650 kilometers in altitude, and that accounts for about
86% of the global total that was expended in that timeframe.
But as worrisome as that metric is, what's almost worse than that is the
actual mass of rocket bodies in the same amount of
time. It's more than tripled, and
this growth rate represents 98% of the global increase in abandoned
mass.
By the contrast, in that same period, the United States left only four
rocket bodies and Russia left only one.
So next slide.
The reason why we're a little bit more concerned about mass
is because of actual explosions of these rocket bodies.
So for all of the reasons that we've been learning about in this class,
we have temperature gradients, we have space environment
effects that actually weaken the materials that those rocket bodies are made of,
and the residual fuel that's left in those rockets can
actually leak out and explode. And this has
actually happened several times in the last four years.
So China, in the last four years, has lost two
CZ-6A rockets and one Jiuque
2. And forgive my pronunciation of some of these names.
I'm not fluent in Chinese, unfortunately.
But as was mentioned in the previous
presentation, these debris at that altitude can linger
for decades or even centuries.
And this is particularly worrisome when we start talking about the mass problem
because Chinese rockets are generally larger than those of other nations.
So when they fragment, there's going to be more stuff.
Also of concern is the fact that these payloads
primarily include satellites for China's
Zhuwang and Qianfan constellations, which is basically their
equivalent to Starlink. So as of right now,
with the launches that we have already mentioned here that we're concerned about,
that accounts for only 200 of a planned 15,000
satellites that are eventually going to be
in that proliferated constellation.
So the bottom line is there's a lot more of these to come.
Next slide.
So just to give a little bit of context to some of those numbers
here. You can see from the table, China,
over the history of manned spaceflight, is not the worst offender.
Russia and the United States, both in terms of
number of
things and total mass, is still
ahead. But if you look at just the last five years,
Russia and the United States have dramatically, and the rest of the world, have
dramatically slowed down in terms of both sheer
numbers and mass, whereas China over the last
five years is vectoring in completely the opposite direction.
So they have more than 30 times the rest of the world in terms of
both raw numbers and mass of things that they're putting into
space. Many of these rocket bodies are in the 800 kilometer to
850 kilometer altitude. And so
just as an example, for the United States to get their proliferated warfighter
space architecture up, we have to go through that to get to the operational
altitude of 1,000 kilometers.
So for a couple of examples here, the Long March 6A rocket that
I mentioned earlier, there was an August 2024 launch.
That explosion resulted in over 1,000 pieces of trackable debris at
810 kilometers. And then the Jiuque 2e,
this picture at the lower right is an actual optical
image of what was left after the explosion of that rocket
body, and this picture is only one month old.
So this
explosion just happened last month. It resulted in 100 pieces of debris.
And
based on the orbitology of that particular explosion, these things now
pose a direct threat to both the ISS and Starlink
constellations.
Next slide.
So as was mentioned in the previous
presentation,
there are some mitigators in terms of both international law
and potential physics-based solutions.
The international best practice, as was mentioned previously, is that
we mandate a number of mitigation measures to
reduce the risk of on-orbit explosions.
This one in particular to the one I'm citing is a United
Nations subcommittee, so there's multiple different governing bodies
here. This one in particular was signed by more than 60
nations, including China. But the problem, of course, is that verification
of compliance is difficult. So
one mitigator, and as was mentioned, the demarcation is
basically 25 years or less for things to de-orbit
on their own. So one mitigator is to leave enough fuel so
that
spent rocket bodies can be de-orbited,
preferably in a controlled manner.
The other mitigator is the manner in which orbit injection is
done in the first place, which means that you always stay below that 25-year
de-orbit threshold. And then you rely on newer modes of
orbit injection, such as electric or other propulsion techniques, to
gradually reach your operational altitude without having to rely on these
large rocket bodies that are the problem in the first place.
China claims to already follow these best practices, and they claim this as of,
again, a month ago in a statement to the UN Committee on Peaceful Uses of Outer
Space. So at this point, it sort of remains to be
seen what's going to happen as they move forward in
populating their own proliferated constellations.
And that is all I have for the presentation.
My references, there's several articles that I cited that are on the
last slide if you want to go follow these links and read more.
These are all really good reads. So that's all I have, and thank you for
your attention on this tonight.
Thank you, Ron.
And then finally, we've got Claire,
who had this video to share, and I will have
to
switch my screen share over to
her presentation.
And here it is.
All right. Good evening, everybody.
My name is Claire Wadman, and I'm presenting on
micrometeoroids and orbital debris, specifically the
design considerations related to these.
So looking at micrometeoroids and orbital debris, or often
abbreviated to MMOD, here's an overview.
Orbital debris are going to be any man-made objects
orbiting the Earth that no longer serve a useful purpose.
So this might be the upper stages of rockets, defunct
satellites, or fragments from satellite collisions or breakups that
are still in Earth orbit.
These objects can reach speeds up to
17,500 miles per hour in low Earth orbit,
which is roughly 10 times the average speed of a bullet.
So extremely high velocities we're talking about.
Going on to micrometeoroids. These are 10 micron to two
millimeter natural solid objects that are moving through
interplanetary space. But for the context of this presentation,
we're primarily concerned with objects that have fallen into the
gravitational well of the Earth and are in Earth
orbit. In both cases, we're often talking about
extremely small objects, but these can still
be highly destructive when colliding with satellites at
these very high
relative velocities, which they very often
are.
Just looking at the evolution of orbital debris.
As of 2024, the European Space Agency
reported 36,240 debris
objects in orbit, and
that only accounts for the objects that they've been able
to track. So typically, anything under about 10
centimeters is not going to be trackable.
So all of those smaller objects aren't counted in
that number.
This graph here, courtesy of the Clean Orbit Foundation,
is looking at from
the dawn of the space age in the early 1960s to
roughly 2020.
The near exponential increase
in orbital debris objects that are in Earth
orbit. Again,
looking at all different types of fragments here, but we're
not counting micrometeoroids in the count on
this graph.
Now considering the risks of MMOD objects.
Looking at the size. So any objects that are going to be
greater than 10 centimeters in size are
trackable, but are too large for effective
shielding. So the potential impact to a satellite
is anywhere from catastrophic damage to complete
destruction.
Then going on to objects that are one to 10 centimeters in
size. The larger objects in this range are
trackable. However, they are still going to
be too large for effective shielding against.
So-
We'll go on to talk about shielding in the design
section of this presentation, but essentially that's an option for
mitigating the risk
due to an impact of an MMOD object.
So looking at the potential impact to a satellite
for the one to 10 centimeter object, that's going to
be moderate to catastrophic damage to the
satellite.
Finally, looking at objects that are less than one centimeter
in size. These objects are not trackable,
however, effective shielding does exist.
So the potential impact there is likely
minor damage. However,
these small amounts of damage can still be
detrimental to a mission over time.
Ultimately, the results of MMOD impacts
can range from complete satellite destruction to minor erosions,
cracks, and dents. However, even these minor effects
can cause very long-term damage to a mission as they build up over
time. The result of these impacts often
depends on the MMOD object size
and the relative velocity between an object and a
satellite. But obviously,
the larger the debris or
micrometeoroid and the higher relative velocity
between the object and the satellite, the worst damage is going to
be done.
Here is just an example of an MMOD impact on the ISS
on one of the service module windows.
A very small fragment hit one of the windows and was able to
produce this chip in the window, which
obviously over time these could build up and cause larger
cracks or structural failures that could lead to extremely
detrimental mission failures.
Now going on to design considerations.
So some of these considerations are used to
mitigate
the effects of an MMOD impact, while some
are used to
reduce the potential for an impact at
all.
So first,
one consideration is designing satellites to just
withstand impacts by small debris objects.
So this can be done by careful material selection,
obviously selecting materials that are going to be the most resilient
to these impacts. And then
also shielding on satellites. So these
are typically sacrificial
layers or just a single layer that are put in front
of the structure of a spacecraft that absorb the shock
from an impact. So a very common one
of these is called a Whipple shield.
The idea had been come up with in the 1940s and is still
in use today. But essentially,
typically aluminum is used to provide either one layer or
multiple layers of shock-absorbing shields, basically
in front of the main spacecraft structure.
Additionally, another design consideration is to
obviously maintain mission performance while reducing
fragmentation from solar radiation.
So we've talked about the space environment
and the potential types of particles that can result in
degradation of satellite materials.
And as these materials degrade,
they can result in fragmentation that
essentially creates orbital debris and become a hazard for other
satellites. So avoiding that is definitely a big
consideration for mission design.
Next, we can increase the quality and
reliability of propellants and batteries to prevent
accidental explosions. So this is another consideration that's
aimed at reducing the
number of debris-causing events in orbit and
ultimately reducing
the amount of debris created in general.
Then
we can look at improving maneuverabilities for
collision avoidance. So in those cases of larger
debris objects that you're not going to be able to shield against
and that an impact from would result in complete destruction of a
satellite,
the best case scenario is maneuvering to avoid a collision.
So improving a satellite's ability to do so is going to
help avoid that risk.
Then finally, post-mission disposal is a big one.
So either graveyard orbits, which are less utilized
orbits that a satellite could be inserted into or
completely de-orbiting where a satellite is going to
reenter
the Earth's atmosphere. And again, these are
design considerations that are aimed at
reducing
the
number of debris objects in orbit and improving the quality of
orbit for other missions.
That essentially sums up the debris considerations and the rest of this
presentation. My sources are all here,
but hopefully we all learned something about micrometeoroids
and orbital debris and the design considerations that are related to
them. Thank you.
Okay, so if those three presentations didn't scare the
pants off of you, I don't know what would
Some things that were particularly eye-opening to
me
were
the fact that we're past the Kessler
threshold, which Trent briefed,
in the 520 to 1,000 kilometer range.
That's a big deal. And the typical cost to
remove one piece of orbital debris is about one million dollars.
Ron's presentation, I thought it was
interesting to know how many Long March, or the
growing problem with China's Long March rockets.
And then Claire,
I'm going to talk about Whipple shields a little later, but they
were originally developed in World War II for
tank protection, and I think that's interesting
because tanks are protecting
humans and
Whipple shields on satellites.
Yeah, Rachel, that's a good one, too.
She didn't realize there was an explosion last month. Yeah.
So that's why we do these presentations.
And I thought that the
relationship between tank shields or tank
protection and satellite protection is a very
comparable one. So I'm not surprised it came from that.
Okay. So,
if you've ever seen a shooting star,
then you have seen probably either
micrometeoroids entering the atmosphere or
Starlinks or the ISS.
You can clearly see. It used to be 20 years ago,
the sky was relatively
benign without a lot of shooting stars and things like that.
Now that's not the case. I've gone out and looked at the International Space
Station, and every time I've done it recently in the
last couple of years, there have been a bunch of Starlink satellites that
you can see more clearly than the ISS.
Micrometeoroids are natural, so we didn't
cause it, but orbital debris is man-made.
Orbital pollution, we did it to ourselves.
Most is less than one centimeter, but at very high speeds,
have lots of kinetic energy, and we're going to look at that tonight.
Debris greater than 1,000 kilometers can last
literally thousands of years.
And orbital debris can include spent rockets,
the things that naturally occur during rocket
separation, such as clamps, pyro bolts, other
hardware,
de-spin cables, which are sometimes used to de-spin satellites
once they're released, metallic fragments, paint,
and remnants of launch vehicle and spacecraft
explosions.
Orbital lifetimes
is given by this chart, at least
according to Pizziconi.
Note,
if you are looking at
a,
let's see here, perigee at 1,400,
roughly.
And I don't know why my pen isn't writing anymore.
Again, sometimes things lock up on me in
Zoom that don't normally do that. So I'm
going to have to
restart this.
Sorry about that. Zoom does this to me sometimes.
I really need to use probably a different platform,
but it seems to work okay most of the time.
And it doesn't help that my delete key is broken,
so.
Let's see. Does anyone know an alternate way of getting out of a
presentation without using Control + Alt + Delete?
Because it's completely locked up on me.
Okay. Well, I'm going to have to shut down and restart my computer,
so please log back on in a minute.
All right. Yeah, sorry. I was on mute, and I was talking to you.
I don't have tons of experience with Zoom, unfortunately, myself.
But yeah, we'll log back on in a minute.
Okay, sounds good.
Okay. Actually, that seems like it did the trick.
So let me see.
Unfortunately, I do not. Okay, so let me
try this again.
Let's get out of that.
Let's get it to do something other than black on black.
Here we go. All right.
So we're back on board.
Okay, so
if you have a perigee of about 1,400.
Whoops. 1,400.
And uh-oh, it seemed to have tossed my
slide down somewhere. Let me see if I can fix that.
There we go.
1,400
and you have 1,400 apogee,
so you're pretty circular.
That debris can last 10,000
years,
and that's very surprising. You wouldn't have to
worry about it. Your grandchildren wouldn't have to worry about it.
But
it's a growing problem for those of us, even in our
lifetimes, to deal with that.
Perigee altitude of 1,100 kilometers right
here, and 1,350
roughly
here can still last over
3,000 years.
And even at 400 kilometers and 400
kilometers, that last a year. So that
is where if you're going to do something ridiculous like blow up your own
satellites,
at least do it in low Earth orbit so it decays and is not up there
for 1,000 years or 300 years or anything like that.
So question for you at this time is, do you
think larger or smaller orbits deorbit
faster? And the answer may be
surprising,
but it depends on the area-to-mass
ratio. Area to mass, so if you start thinking about
that. Hey, Jordan. Welcome back.
Thank you.
That is proportional to one over the characteristic length.
So if it's a cube, it would be whatever
the length of one side is.
Larger objects, think about this, larger objects
have smaller area-to-mass ratios,
and the deorbit time is longer, in
fact, than for smaller objects. And that kind of makes
sense
intuitively for this reason,
and I'll go
through a little bit of math here, but then I'll explain it in some terms that
may be useful. We have our force of drag is
one-half density coefficient of drag,
area, velocity squared.
And it seems like force of drag would be directly
proportional to
area. But what really matters is the
acceleration, which is the force of drag divided
by the mass. So now the
acceleration due to drag, or deceleration due to
drag, I might say,
would be one-half row CDa
over mV
squared. So that a
over m ratio
high means you would slow down faster.
So why is a over m proportional to one
over L?
You might
realize that area is proportional to length squared.
Volume is proportional to length
cubed,
or is length cubed if it's a square.
So the mass is the density of the material
times the volume.
So mass is proportional to
L cubed, depending on the density.
So area to mass ratio is proportional to
L squared over L cubed, which is
one over L.
So if you take an example of
aluminum cubes,
if we have a small aluminum cubed, we have an area
of
one
centimeter squared, and we have a mass
proportional to one centimeter cube, proportional to the
volume.
Area over mass would be one over one centimeter
cubed.
Whereas for a large one, we would have an area
of 10 squared centimeter squared
and a mass proportional to
10 cubed centimeter cubed,
and now the area to mass is
proportional to
or
nearly equal to one over centimeter
or one tenth of a centimeter. So the larger
Area has the smaller area to mass ratio,
so you get less deceleration. A way to think about
this is you can imagine having an empty cardboard
box flying out the
window of your car or through something that has a lot of wind,
and you could have a refrigerator and if they
have the same frontal areas,
the wind would have a much harder time slowing down the
refrigerator than it would the
cardboard box. And that is because of its inertia.
So that's the way I think about it. The large aluminum cube
would have more inertia than the small aluminum cube, and
hence it's harder to stop. So same thing happens in
orbit.
Catalogs of orbital debris.
Payloads include functional and
non-functional spacecraft. Mission-related
debris, rocket bodies is obvious.
Mission-related debris is the intentional separation of
objects from payloads. Breakup debris
is from intentional or unintentional
fragmentation of an orbiting body, and
anomalous debris is from unplanned separation of
an object from a payload,
which could often be things like thermal blanket
degradation or solar panels getting
pieces knocked off due to orbital debris and stuff like that.
So I have a little video clip. Let me know if you can see this.
It should work from my slides.
Whoops. Don't want to show that.
And ISS, this is Houston.
Yep, there it is.
Okay.
Explorer to Houston.
Go ahead, Houston.
Mission abort. Repeat, mission abort.
Initiate emergency disconnect from Hubble. Begin re-entry procedure.
ISS, initiate emergency evacuation.
Copy all. Houston ended work. Max, immediate return to Explorer.
Repeat, immediate return to Explorer.
Copy. Explorer from airlock.
Airlock engage. Ready to receive.
Houston, elaborate.
Debris from the missile strike has caused a chain reaction, hitting other
satellites and creating new debris traveling faster than a
high-speed bullet up to its current altitude. How copy?
Copy all. Put a bow on it, Dr. Stone.
I can't.
The port's still initializing.
I'm not going to ask you again.
One second.
Not one second. Now. Shut it down.
That's an order.
Sorry. Sorry, I've got to conduct a port.
Initiate emergency disconnect from the Hubble.
All right, Tariq, let's do this. Roger that. Houston, update.
Well, we have a full-on chain reaction.
It's been confirmed that it's the unintentional side effect of the Russians
striking one of their own satellites.
They shot down their own satellite? Right at disposal.
Most likely a spy sat gone bad, now shrapnel.
We're ready to disengage HSP.
Launch for basic in three, two, one.
Explorer, new data coming through.
What's the fallback, Houston?
It's not good. Most of our systems are gone.
Debris chain reaction is out of control and rapidly expanding.
Multiple satellites are down and they keep on falling.
Define multiple satellites.
Most of them are gone. Telecommunication systems are dead.
Expect a communication blackout at any moment in time.
Mission control to Explorer, 09:00.
Half of North America just lost their Page Plus.
Explorer, repeat. Expect a communication blackout at any moment.
Copy that.
Get ready for it.
Explorer, this is Kowalski. Confirming visual contact with the debris.
Debris is from a BFF sat. I repeat, I have-
Dr. Stone requesting faster transport.
We have to go. We have to go, go, go.
Getting report meteorological conditions. Over.
Houston and Explorer, copy. Explorer, Dr.
Stone requesting faster transport to Bay Area. Explorer, do you copy?
Explorer, permission to retrieve Dr. Stone.
You're go, Kowalski. Houston, Explorer.
Copy. Hello,
Houston. Hello. Hello. Crap.
Get the hell out of here.
Oh, don't wait for her.
It's stuck.
Man down. Man down.
Explorer-
Dr. Stone. Dr.
Stone, detach.
Stone, detach. Stone, detach that arm from the carrier you fool.
Listen to my voice. You need to focus.
I'm losing visual of you. In two seconds, I won't be able to track
you. Steve, detach. I can't see you anymore.
Do it now.
Houston, I've lost visual of Dr. Stone.
Okay. So
pretty intense event there.
Let me see if I can-
And ISS-
Didn't need to do that. Let's stop sharing for a minute
and then share my slides again.
Terrifi-
I can't seem to go
onto the next page.
So anyway,
while I'm trying to get this pulled back up,
I would like to say that that's
pretty far out, right? Well,
does anyone know what movie that was from?
That was from the movie "Gravity,"
and that was from 2013.
And that was due to the fact that one of the
Russians
hit one of their satellites. So what really
happened is
in 2021, they actually did that,
and I knew that
immediately because at the time-
Whoops.
I didn't mean to do that. Let me try it again.
Abort. Repeat.
So I was at a AIAA conference, American
Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics conference,
in
Las Vegas in November of 2021. This happened
during that conference, and that's all anyone talked about for
the rest of the conference, because that was a pretty serious
breach of some of the UN guidelines.
And-
Olive Garden's Calabrian summer-
There we go. Finally went to the next slide.
And ISS, this is Houston.
Whoops.
Explorer, this is Houston.
Go ahead.
I don't know why
Zoom is being such a problem for me tonight, but it is.
And ISS, this is Houston.
Explorer, this is...
Hey,
glad
you all are still here. I got kicked off for a moment.
So,
let me go ahead and share my slides again.
But yeah, that's all anyone talked about the whole
remainder of the conference there.
And like
Trent mentioned earlier in his current events
presentation, this is basically the Kessler effect,
collisional cascading. It was
a term that was developed by Dr. Donald
Kessler, who worked for NASA in
1978. So he had the
forevision to see that this was coming,
and it creates a very unstable environment, cascading type of
environment. And the fragmentations from the
collisions are generated faster than the drag
could remove them. So what did the Russians do in 2021?
They saw this movie and said, "Yeah, let's duplicate it." No, not really.
Hopefully not.
But no country has publicly
conducted another debris-generating ascent
ASAT test since then. We've had Long March
rockets blow up and things like that,
but
no countries have purposely done that since then.
The target was their Cosmos 1408
intelligence satellite. It had a mass of 2,200
kilograms at an altitude of 480 kilometers.
Fortunately, that's not super high, but it was in the
same region that the ISS flies
in. It resulted in 1,500 trackable,
greater than 10-centimeter objects, and it's
estimated that there were hundreds of thousands of smaller
objects that were generated.
They launched a
direct ascent missile from the ground, and many
fragments passed through the ISS's direct path.
So let's see what one of those were.
Hey, Mark. Good morning. Sorry for the early call.
We were recently informed of a satellite breakup and
need to have you guys start reviewing the safe haven
procedure. It's nine decimal two one.
We are planning on performing through block eight, which will
include closing the radial hatches.
The time of concern is 0600.
Copy. Nine decimal two one. We're looking at executing that three
step eight, and including closing the
lateral hatches, and final concern is zero
six hundred.
Okay.
That's a good read. We have a step on the ground to configure
before you guys close those radial hatches.
We will be sure to let you know when we are ready for you to perform your steps.
Sounds good. Thanks for the heads up.
To answer your question earlier about suits, we can support you getting into
suits at your discretion. It's your call.
Just to note that the Soyuz crew is not in suits, and then heads up 15
minutes to the next debris field past TCA.
Endurance copies. And is the conjunction still yellow risk, or has it
changed?
It's an equivalent yellow for the next debris pass.
And then also, we are estimating that the
probability of a hit to Dragon would be lower than the rest of ISS.
And Houston, Endurance. Is
SpaceX on console to have a conversation on Dragon to ground about forward actions
if we do have a hit?
Endurance, Houston.
So you have like-
Yes.
SpaceX is on console.
If it's under half an hour, we were thinking about coming back on the
station. If it's more than half an hour, we were thinking to stay suited
and potentially come back home. This is all if Dragon takes a hit.
Endurance, Houston. Alteration to that proposal.
If Dragon takes a hit, we will get you back on
station.
Copy. We'll come back on the station regardless if Dragon takes a hit.
And Endurance, Houston. Onset square one, just want to reiterate that we think it's
small likelihood that Dragon would get an impact.
Endurance, copy. Thanks.
Yeah. So that was pretty severe. The
astronauts on board the ISS were ready to move into the
Dragon
for separation in case the ISS got hit.
So this was a huge event for the
astronauts,
and this is how it propagated.
There it goes.
And note that all of the
pieces have different
ballistic coefficients, which we talked about a couple of lessons ago with the
neutral environment. So that's why they tend to spread out the way they do,
among other reasons, but that's one of the main reasons they spread
out. And it turned out to be right in the path of the ISS,
so not a good situation for anyone involved.
They mention the yellow status.
So I wanted to spend a minute or two talking
about the ISS pizza box.
This is what it's called.
And what is established here
is a...
There's my red again. Is a plus and minus of half a kilometer,
and along this direction, and this
direction is plus and minus
25 kilometers. And if anything comes within that
region with certain probabilities
of impact, then that's what they establish
as yellow or red. So in this case, it was
yellow, and that means the
probability is about two in 20,000.
And that means yellow status, and that
means you may or may not need to move out of its way.
If the probability is one in 10,000,
that would be red status,
in which case
you will definitely need to do a red debris
avoidance maneuver. And in that case, they rely on one
of the docked vehicles, just like they do when they need to lift their orbit,
Soyuz, Dragon, whatever's on board,
Starship.
Not Starship.
The other one that Boeing makes.
15 debris avoidance maneuvers per year is about
what's average now. So that's
amazing that we have that many close encounters.
This is a video which I guess I'll show
now that I've clicked on it.
2011, the crew of the International Space Station
learns their lives are in imminent danger.
Space debris is heading towards them.
NBC, Jeff Rossen watching all of this. Jeff, good morning to you.
Space junk was on a collision course with the International Space
Station, spotted so late, there was no time to move out of the
way. Instead, the six astronauts got the order from mission
control.
The probabilities are still in the red threshold, and we are planning
to have you shelter in place.
If all else fails, the astronauts on board the space station can
climb into those Soyuz space capsules and wait to
see whether a collision actually takes place.
If it does, they can, in a few seconds, detach from whatever's
left of the space station, and then immediately try to return to Earth.
Mission Control orders the astronauts to the Soyuz lifeboats.
It's only the second time a crew has been told to potentially
abandon ship.
Once we got all the hatches closed, and when we were all buttoned up in our Soyuz
spacecraft, there really was nothing to do but wait.
We discussed, "Okay, if things get really bad, this is what we're going to do, and
we're going to undock." We started to talk about that, and then it was just
a waiting game after that.
But we didn't know if it was going to hit it or not.
Finally, after 15 minutes, word
arrives from mission control.
When the object passed the space station, we got a call from mission control that
it was all clear.
And it turned out that this object passed within a football field of the space
station, and relative velocity was eight miles per second.
So it was a fairly large object traveling that fast.
It probably would've destroyed the space station had it
hit.
So that's pretty intense.
To give you an idea or to translate eight miles
per second, that's about 13 kilometers per second, and
28,800 miles per hour.
So very speedy, high kinetic energy
debris.
Previous major ASAT test, United States have been guilty
of it also in 2008. 2007,
China's, which was mentioned in a couple of
the current events,
was at an altitude of 865 kilometers, which means it's going to
stay up there a lot longer.
Russia's in 2021 was at
a lower
altitude, but it still is still a
lot of stuff up there. The United States and the India test,
most of that has been reentered.
We expect China, 865
kilometers, to be up there for decades.
Chinese ASAT,
this is how the debris propagated.
Okay, so a couple of programs that you can use to
track space debris. So I'm going to share
this with you all. You probably have your own favorite program if you're
into space debris at all or satellite tracking,
but here is one called Heavens-Above.
And what it does... Let's see,
I'm sharing my
screen, not the Heavens-Above link. Let me pull that up.
Is it is a program that you can use to
look at where satellites currently are,
and to give you an idea of what's
available here. You can do a live sky view.
You can see what
satellites are available at what time, what constellations you can see.
Of course, there's apps you can get on your phone to do
that, but I thought that's kind of interesting.
The Starlink constellation, this was
amazing. This was crazy to me how many Star-
This is only Starlinks, by the way.
And, they are now polar. They're pretty much in
every orbit that you can imagine, and this
is what the current Starlink constellation looks like.
That's not even including the China, I don't remember
what it's called, it starts with a Q,
mega constellation. That's not including the Kuiper constellation
that Amazon's going to put up. This is only Starlink.
One thing that you can do with this is you can look at, let's just look at the
Hubble Space Telescope, if it's still here. Yeah, it still is.
You can look at dates where you can see visible
passes. So if you want to find out more about where the Hubble
Space Telescope is, you can get info on
that, when it launched.
You can get-
Orbit information. It'll show you
both the ground track as well
as the orbit itself from a couple of different views,
and its classical orbital elements.
And then you can also see when it's going to pass
over. Let's look at 20 July, because that's a pretty
good one, and it shows when the satellite will
pass over and in which directions it's going.
The other thing you can do is look up
in the satellite database,
specific missions, and the one that I was involved in,
and of course, I'm guilty of leaving space debris up there,
but we did that pretty regularly in the '90s.
I'm going to look at 23567 and
23568,
and you'll see a USA 110,
and that is the mission I was a
mission manager for, and it will give you the same
information. Whoops. Didn't mean
to do that.
What is
up there,
and as long as you know the mission number or you just know the
mission name, you can do this yourself.
And you can find out the orbit that it's in.
It's not going to give you a whole lot of information other than it was at geo
at a inclination of 15 degrees. It
makes a figure-eight ground track, just like you
learn probably in astrodynamics.
And, the other vehicle associated with
that was
the upper stage that was left up there.
And you can take a look at this, and you can see the orbit is
about the same, 18 degrees inclination,
geo,
with a ground track over
the western part of Africa.
So you can find out a lot from this. Another
program that I like to use is called
spaceaware.io,
and let me share that one with you.
And this shows all of the satellites currently in
orbit.
And you can see clearly the geo
constellation. You can see
clearly,
as you get in closer, you can see inclinations not at
zero, so
geosynchronous. But as you get in closer,
you can also pick up
a lot of the
sun synchronous orbits here, as well as Molniya orbits.
So you can click on any one of these, and it will
tell you what the ground track looks like and what that
particular satellite is, if it's
known. Another one
I like to use is space-track.org.
So let me go to that one.
Space-track.org. This one I am logged into,
and it'll tell you, you can go to geo
satellites.
Let me see, where is that at?
Geosynchronous report, and it will tell you all the satellites
currently in geo. You can click on this and get its
two-line element set.
And another one.
Nope. There is one more.
I did include in the slides a TLE decoder in case you're
interested in what the two-line elements are, and you're not familiar with
that. The last one I wanted to briefly mention
is
Astrograph.
And this one takes a little longer to load,
but it's kind of cool because you can filter it
by, let's see, country of origin. Yeah, we know
we got a lot of stuff out there. How much of it is due to the United
States? Oh, you can clearly pick up that Molniya orbit on this one
too. You see the
very eccentric orbit that goes out nearly to geo.
If we want to see what US satellites there
are,
a lot of them are ours,
but not all of them. Of course, many of the low Earth orbits are
Starlink,
but I was kind of interested,
"Hmm, what satellites does
maybe Iran have up there?" And it will
tell you exactly what those are.
They're mostly low Earth orbit, but you can click on here, and it'll
tell you the name and origin of the country,
and a lot of the information about that.
And then I thought, "Hmm, I wonder what
Kazakhstan is up to."
And yes, they do have a few satellites up
there. So this is another great resource
for you in case you're bored one day and want to look
at those.
So what type of damage can this space
debris impart? And this was kind of
mentioned, but not explicitly during the
current events presentations. The size of the particle,
even down to a tenth of a millimeter, can cause surface
erosion. And one millimeter can cause
serious damage because KE is one-half
MV squared, and the greater
the size, the greater the mass, and the greater
the kinetic energy would be, especially going at seven kilometers per
second in LEO.
Three millimeters, we have the kinetic energy of a
bowling ball. I would not want to be hit by that.
And at one centimeter, it would be like having a safe dropped on your
head at 100 miles per hour.
These are relative velocities reported here.
This is a famous one from the shuttle
window. There are ones that have
impacted the ISS window.
With the shuttle, they could bring it back down and replace it.
With the ISS, you can't really do that.
So,
less than two kilometers per second, no big deal. You can shatter.
Molten state, greater than 11 kilometers per second, and this
will be the speeds that
micrometeorites are at. You can vaporize
the material, get into a molten state.
So this is homework problem two. Kinetic energies of space
objects can be large. Plot the kinetic energy in joules versus
diameter of a particle on a log-log scale.
Assume the particle is at the same altitude as the ISS.
So you can look that up. It varies depending on whether it's
boosted lately or not. How does this compare to the kinetic energy of a
small, medium, and large satellite?
And then based on your results, what are the most susceptible?
So this is what I'm looking at, looking for the
diameter in centimeters and make sure it's a log-log
plot,
and the kinetic energy
in joules. And that
should
result in something. If you start at zero, it start at zero.
Let's assume that we have some finite size of the particle.
You will get a
profile that looks like
an increasing slope, of course. And then for the
kinetic energies of the small, medium, and large satellite, you should
have three horizontal lines here, with, of course, the
largest being
the highest kinetic energy. And from that, you can tell
that would be a very bad case, that would be a bad case, that
would be a bad case. So,
that's what you're going to do on homework two.
Homework problem three. Now we're looking at the
equations
governing the kinetic energy of a bowling ball or a...
Yeah, I think we're using bowling balls. Yeah, bowling ball.
Two-kilogram bowling ball.
Calculate the impact speed of the debris, which is one
G piece of space debris, and
it would be equivalent to a gravitational potential energy
loss
by two-kilogram bowling ball dropped from 100
meters. And
what you can do is you can equate this, one-half MV
squared, is equal to
MGH,
where this is the bowling ball and this is the debris, and you can
solve for the impact speed. And then in part B, I
ask you to do the opposite. Given this impact speed,
what would be the height that a two-kilogram bowling ball would need to
fall? And your answer there might be surprising.
How does this compare to the kinetic energy of the space debris, and
which poses the greater threat?
Although I don't ask you to quantify part D.
So how is this tracked? US Space Surveillance Network,
primary source. They're responsible
for keeping a public catalog
of
debris
and predicting conjunctions, issuing collision warnings, and
providing launch and re-entry support
using a worldwide network. And this is just showing a few of these.
These are the publicly known ones anyway.
LEO can track from five to 10 centimeters, GEO from
a third to one meter,
and
about 33% of those checked are
functional.
There are about 400,000 observations made per
day. Another secondary, not necessarily
secondary, I guess it depends on whose mission it is, is NASA's
Orbital Debris Program Office at Johnson Space
Center. They specialize more in small
debris using specialized radars.
And then there's other countries and other agencies.
The European Space Agency has a space debris
office. Commercial companies, LeoLab, Slingshot
Aerospace, um Other national
agencies, Japan,
JAXA, Japan, DLR, Germany, France, UK,
Italy.
And you might wonder, how is that tracked?
Well, you see on the left there, left top, a ground-based
radar, which can track mostly in LEO.
And then on the right, you see an optical telescope which
can track
MEO and GEO, and then space-based sensors that can help with
everything. So space-based surveillance satellite, for
example.
This chart was shown by one of the presenters earlier today, so
I'm not going to go into it. I did want to tell you
briefly what the primary culprit
is, and that would be unidentified.
That is what UI stands for, unidentified.
The rest of them are kind of obvious.
Rocket mission, rocket debris, rocket frags,
fragmentations, rocket body, payload mission
related, payload debris, payload fragmentation,
and payloads themselves.
Trends, you can see that there's many more unidentified recently,
and many more payload missions due to the mega
constellations we have going on now.
Top 10 space debris contributions, which is different from the
ASAT test, although some of them overlap, was the China
ASAT test. We already talked about this, but there
are accidental collisions that also have
contributed to it. The Russians
had a Cosmos satellite, their Cosmos,
collide with an Iridium satellite, and that was at a pretty high
altitude, so that created a lot of
fragments that will be up there a very long time.
Space debris damage. So this is from the space shuttle days.
Of course, we could bring that back down and look at the damage, whereas we can't
do that with the International Space Station easily.
And this was a hole here in the
external radiator.
I'm sorry, that's the next slide. This is the
debris
that impacted the lower surface.
And to give you an idea, this covered 54 shuttle missions,
of which 43 were inspected for damage.
1,385 impacts on the
window alone. 76 required window replacement,
32 were orbital debris, 17
micrometeoroids, so much more due to orbital debris,
and 27 were unknown. And the vast majority of those
were aluminum,
and a few due to paint chips, and the rest of them were
copper, steel, and unknown effects.
Damage to the ISS.
Mostly only localized damages, but there was an impact that hit
the Canada arm
in 2021, and the particle was only about one
millimeter.
It punctured the thermal blanket and left a hole in the boom structure,
and this was
a one millimeter object. Fortunately, it missed all the critical
wiring, but you can see the damage here,
and they called it the lucky strike because it didn't
create more damage. Relative velocity was believed to be
about 10 to 15 kilometers per second.
So that was because the ISS was going
at seven kilometers per second, and the debris was coming in the
opposite direction. Comparable to a rifle bullet,
to give you an earthly
analogy.
This is the radiator damage done to the ISS.
There was a hole in the external ammonia radiator,
and this was serious because it caused about
72 liters
of coolant to leak into space.
And they postponed a spacewalk because of this to
evaluate the contamination risk to make sure the astronauts would not
get
negatively impacted. This was a window impact on the
ISS, and what they do, instead of just having an
open window all the time, they close shutters over it.
So that provides some protection when it's not being used
actively.
Some space debris models are shown here.
The reason I show this is your homework problem is going to
be to research an orbit debris modeling program,
either from this list or something you research on your own,
and then discuss it, who publishes it, who maintains it, summarize
its predicted effects.
Okay, so that was it for
this part of the lecture tonight.
Let me get out of some of these
open windows here.
And we'll go on to what we can do about that.
And then we'll go into some of the regulations and
guidelines, not really laws in place, but there are some
guidelines, and we'll take a look at those.
So here we go, sharing part two.
This is a little shorter than the first one.
And what we're going to look at is
micro
meteoroids.
So let's start off with a few definitions.
A meteoroid is a small
piece of a meteorite.
Meteors, before we knew what they were, we
came up with the term meteors, and those are the
flashes of light.
So they don't really mean a physical phenomena, but
those are the flashes of light. And again, that term was developed before we
really knew what they were.
So the reason you get flashes is the meteoroids
ionize the ambient
atmosphere around that very high,
fast-moving meteoroid. Meteorites are
the remains that hit the surface of the Earth.
And what we'll be talking about mostly
is, oops, I meant to say up here micrometeoroids.
And the meteoroids are mass less
than one kilogram.
So meteor showers are a little different from that.
Meteor showers occur when the Earth's orbit
intersects the orbital path of a cloud of dust
left by the breakup or the trail of a comet.
So those are a little different, even though we call them meteor showers.
Modeling methods. Okay, so before we go into that, I wanted to
let you know there are several. There's analytic,
and that's what we're going to use in this class, and there's also
digital.
So analytic, the two
most popular ones are
Korolev,
which was developed in 1969,
and it was a meteoroid stream model.
The one we're going to look at today is Grün,
which was a 1985 analytical model, and that's still what's
presented in both Tribble and Pizzichini.
Digital, we have lots of choices here.
ESA has a meteoroid engineering
model,
but I didn't want to get into the details of that in this class, just because we
don't have time.
2005.
And another popular one is
NASA's meteoroid
engineering model,
developed in 2004.
So we're going to concentrate on
the Grün model,
and that is shown on the next page. This is what it is given
by. The average cumulative
flux is given by
this parameter times a shielding factor times a
gravitational focusing factor.
So what we're interested in a lot of times is the flux in
the particles, and that would be in particles per meter squared
year. And then that is consisting
of these three different factors here, all
dependent on mass. So mass is the only variable
here.
And that should be F3. My undergraduate students pointed that out to me the
other day.
Shielding factor
is important because that is a direct ratio.
That is a direct factor in the cumulative
flux. The shielding factor is,
in free space, it's equal to one, not within the field of view.
But what happens as you get
closer is the Earth actually shields the
spacecraft from it, especially if you have a spacecraft over here and you
get a micrometeoroid coming from that direction.
The Earth is going to shield you from a lot of that.
So if you're in free space, you get no
protection. If the orientation of the
surface, you don't know which way it's oriented, is random, you use this.
But most often for Earth-orbiting satellites, we
will use cosine of theta, where sine of theta
is given by the radius
to the top of the atmosphere, divided by,
this would typically be the semimajor axis or the
radius of the circular orbit if it's circular.
For radius to the top of the atmosphere,
assume 100 kilometers for this class
And then finally, the gravitational focusing
factor
means that the Earth focuses the micrometeoroids towards
the Earth and helps shield the spacecraft, not just from the
geometry, but from its gravitational pull.
So,
that is given by this factor here, and I have already
defined radius of the atmosphere and
semi-major axis.
So that might be important, but what you are
probably mostly interested in is,
okay, that's great. When am I going to get hit?
What's the probability of me getting hit?
So this is given by collision probabilities,
and this is a Poisson's distribution,
and this was mostly empirically determined.
It can be used to determine the probability of a specific number of
events, K,
in the time interval, t.
So you must know the average number of
events per unit time, which in this case is
defined as lambda.
So the collision probability
of no hits of a single hit
is one minus the probability of no hits.
And that is given by
mainly this equation. I'm going to do an example using this.
And
let
me find my solution to this real quick. Here we go.
This is an example. So an orbital debris digital software
program estimates that for the ISS, the total flux density of
particles greater than one centimeter is
8.4 times 10 to the minus 6. So
in the notation given by the previous slide,
we've got F of M is 8.4
times 10 to the minus 6 particles
per
meter squared year,
and the area is 10
meters squared, and the probability of being
impacted at least one time is given
by one minus E to the minus
FM A T.
So in one year,
this would equal to minus 8.4 times
10 to the minus 6,
meters cubed times one year, or
you would get 8.4 times 10 to the minus
5. So that would correspond to a percent
likelihood of
0.0084%.
So how would that change if it was over five years?
That would be
0.042%.
Too many dots there.
And then for P, since it's a direct relationship
with the time
for 10 years would be
0.084%. So you can see how that
probability increases.
And this is for one year,
five years,
10 years.
So homework problem number four. You're going to do something similar
to this, but what I'd like you to do is compare the likelihood of satellites
being impacted by micrometeoroids.
So first, you're going to plot the flux density
using these equations here,
that equation right there. And you're going to have to
estimate,
well, given mass.
Clearly state your assumptions and what you use for all of these
factors. And for
example,
make sure you use a log-log scale.
So for example, if you're plotting flux density, you
would have on the x-axis,
mass
in grams, and you would have the flux particles
per year on the y-axis. And if you're using a
log-log scale, you should get trends that look
like this,
decaying, because it makes sense that if you have small
particles, you're going to have more flux density, whereas you have bigger
particles, you will have less
flux
density, and that's quantified by mass.
Part B, how much average time in years you're going to use the same equation
we did before
Except now you're given the probability
of 0.01%, solve for time for
each of those sizes,
and then what can you conclude about the likelihood of damage to satellites
with an expected mission life of 10 years?
Okay.
The Inter-Agency Space Debris Coordination Committee
was mentioned by one of our
current events
presenters today, and they have established protected
regions around which you want to minimize,
first off, going into in the first place, but sometimes you can't avoid that.
But you definitely want to minimize debris released in those
regions. And it basically includes all of LEO,
anything in LEO,
so all altitudes less than 2,000
kilometers, and that's a little higher than our typical definition of
LEO, but it's included in there. And then
GEO, we look at inclinations between plus
and minus 15 degrees, or 15 degrees.
And plus or minus 200 kilometers from the GEO belt.
And I'll explain how we get to the GEO
graveyard based on certain parameters.
It's not just 200 kilometers above.
It depends on the properties of the satellite.
The GEO graveyard is often advertised as being between
216 kilometers. It is super
synchronous, so if you look at the ground track, it will actually
drift westward.
And the question always comes up, why don't we just de-orbit
everything? But to give you an idea, the delta V
required to de-orbit from average,
required to de-orbit from GEO
is about 1.5
kilometers per second, which is huge, whereas a
Hohmann transfer
to graveyard
is about 11 meters per second. So it's
a lot more cost-effective and propellant-effective
to go into the graveyard orbit.
There are two conditions to get you there.
One of them is that your perigee altitude or your change in
perigee altitude is about 235
kilometers plus or minus, or plus, I mean,
a factor dependent on your radiation coefficient.
Radiation pressure coefficient, and we'll talk a
lot more about that when we get to the
radiation lectures,
and that is typically between one and two.
And it also depends on this area-to-mass ratio.
So there's not really, "Oh, all GEO satellites go to GEO
plus 200 kilometers." It depends on the
characteristics of the satellite itself.
So what should satellite providers be doing?
Well, they should
avoid planned releases
and other orbital debris releases during
normal operations. And this would include lens caps that you
take off, any covers, any clamps that would be
released. Make sure those are tethered like we tether our
astronauts when they go on spacewalks.
And then we also need to make sure
all sources of energy are depleted
before we put that satellite to rest.
So that would include propellants,
batteries,
high-pressure vessels,
self-destructive
components,
flywheels,
momentum wheels
should be depleted
at the end of life
to keep that energy from being passed along to another
object up there.
We also
want to make sure that debris
by,
of course this is common sense, produced by
in-orbit collisions
Is minimized.
And doing number two will help do that.
And then post-mission disposal. And I already talked
on the previous couple of slides about
picking a perigee,
delta perigee height, and that equation we looked at
before.
Okay. So on to part two of part two.
Let's see. I do have
one more set of slides to go through.
And in this set,
we'll take a look at the UN guidelines, not in a whole lot of detail
because they're just that. They're guidelines.
But
we're going to look at some design solutions.
Here
we go.
And particularly, we're going to take a look at
Whipple design, just a basic Whipple design.
And you do have a homework problem on that also, so let's
take a look at that.
Okay.
An example of what space debris can happen.
So we're going to look at protection options and what are the UN guidelines,
although I'm not going to go into those in a lot of detail other than
mention the fact that these have been violated numerous times,
and we don't do anything about it.
So one thing that we can do, thermal blankets
themselves
mostly protect or can protect
a lot against dust grains of rocky debris, and
it helps with dissipating the energy due to those high-energy
particles. Thermal blankets are
often aluminized mylar or kapton separated by
stuff in between, and it's often the first line
of defense. It can reduce the
risk of secondary damage, and the
multilayer insulation can also trap
fragments. So it kind of acts like a padded jacket that cushions
tiny impacts.
Operational things that we can do.
Obviously, if you've got something sensitive, don't point it towards the ramp
side or the side that is getting impact the most
from the particles.
Fly in regions where there's less debris.
You don't always have the choice on doing that.
Or using Whipple shields or some type of leading edge
bumper, which was briefed earlier
in one of our current events presentations.
So what it can do is it can absorb and disperse impact energy.
It can cause incoming
debris to fragment or vaporize before it reaches the
spacecraft critical components.
The ISS uses a lot of Whipple shields
all over,
especially around the most sensitive components.
It's often layered, like is shown here on the right, and it's
especially good for vulnerable areas such as radar
sensors and antennas.
Other solutions. Stage your rockets.
Don't use single stage to orbit, and when you do stage them, don't just leave them
up there.
Increase satellite lifetime so there's less debris up there.
Vent fuel tanks. We talked about that a while ago.
Move inactive satellites out of the way, and move out of
large
debris paths. So you might need to do some maneuvering like
was mentioned in the current events presentation, where Starlink did a lot of those
over the past year.
Okay. So
I ask you in problem seven, describe three of the technology
solutions to help reduce the harmful effects of space debris,
and explain how it could be implemented and one
example. So you can research any of these prior areas that
I looked at, or you can look at other areas that
could be researched. But I'm looking for three of those.
So how do you design Whipple shields?
What they do, well, they help dissipate the energy
due to debris. So it's here. It doesn't necessarily go
straight through.
It can create a debris cloud, which may
still, some debris may impact it, but they'll be much
smaller particles and won't do as much damage
Now, what I try to do in my undergraduate
classes, I wrote out all these equations, but I
found that it was just easier to copy the equations directly from the
textbook. This comes from Pizzicani,
and this is how you design
the
bumper thickness. Whoops.
Bumper thickness and the wall thickness for
your
particular design. And the wall thickness would be the thickness behind it.
The bumper thickness would be the thickness of the Whipple shield.
And we're just looking at a two-shield
design. So this would be your wall, and this would be your bumper.
So not looking at all the layers in between.
CB is dependent
on the S divided by D ratio,
where this is your shielding
or standoff,
and D is the projectile diameter. So it depends on
that ratio,
and that would typically be in... Oh, it says here centimeters. Good.
And then you would need to know a bumper density and a projectile
density.
I've given you specifics on those on your homework problem.
And then your wall thickness is given by
this equation, and I do have the three parameters here
mentioned. So theta is the impact angle.
So if you have a piece of debris coming in, this would be the impact
angle. The worst case
I would use for your homework problem would be theta
equals zero, straight on impact. That would be the worst case.
So this is your homework problem nine.
Spacecraft with a Whipple shield is required to survive the impact of a
meteoroid with a density of 1.6 grams per centimeter
cubed.
The shield and spacecraft are made of
aluminum, so you've got the density for both of
those, and you have a yield stress, which is sigma
in the above equation. So that is sigma right
there, yield stress. Now, notice,
this is kind of weird. You got some weird units here.
So CW is centimeter to the minus
three-fourths grams to the one-third
second per kilometer, for example.
Notice that sigma is given in
ksi,
1,000 psi,
and everything else is given in SI units.
The equations account for that. That's where some of these factors come
into. So you don't need to worry about converting
psi to pascals or anything like that.
You can use those directly.
You will get a
plot.
So what you will be doing is you will be plotting
the...
The wall density
is pretty constant. It is
the bumper thickness
that will vary
based on...
Let's see. I'll verify this in just a minute, but based on
the
spacing.
So I'll pull up the homework problem and verify that, but I can give you an idea of
what that will look like.
Now, finally,
space debris mitigation guidelines.
So there are several NASA standards.
A couple of other standards were mentioned in the current events
presentations, and
these are members of the IADC.
Notice China, Russia, US, Japanese,
pretty much all the countries are, most of the countries are involved
in this that have active space programs.
And what are the UN guidelines? So we've been over
most of these before. I just wanted to go over a few of them to
say how
these are just guidelines, and quite a few of them have been
violated. Limit debris release during normal operations.
We talked about that. Minimize the potential for breakups during
operational phases. We talked about that.
Limit the probability of accidental collision in orbit.
Not sure there's a whole lot you can do with a dead satellite about
that. Avoid intentional destruction.
Have we violated that? Yes.
The US, Russia, China, and India have all violated that,
and there's really no repercussions.
Minimize potential for post-mission breakups resulting
from stored energy. That's why you want to deplete your
tanks and things like that.
Limit the long-term presence of spacecraft and launch vehicle orbital states in
LEO.
I think we're pretty good about doing that.
Limit the long-term interference of spacecraft and launch vehicle orbital
stages in GEO. I'm guilty of not doing
that.
And next, we'll talk about the vacuum environment.
Before I moved on, I wanted to pull up the homework
assignment, or at least give you an idea of what that last
problem will look like.
This'll be homework five
And I probably shouldn't be recording this, but that's okay.
This is if you want to stop and get all the answers to homework,
there it is. But this is
about what your wall thickness,
your bumper... Your wall thickness should look like.
I think I said before bumper thickness, but that is your
general outline of what your wall thickness can look from.
Now, the magnitude it goes to will depend on your assumptions,
but you should be evaluating it from about 0 to 25
centimeters. So clearly state your assumptions on
that problem.
Okay, and that's all I have for tonight.
Thank the three of you who stayed on through
the end of this recording, and for everyone else, I hope you
enjoy listening to this recording and doing the
homework.
We'll see you next week.
Thanks, Ron.
Awesome. Thank you. Thank you so much for your time.
Thanks, Jordan.
Great lecture.
Sorry. I
don't think you were sharing your screen for the estimated
amounts. I know obviously if you don't want to record that, I understand.
Oh. Yeah, let me go back to that,
and yeah, I didn't want to show my solution.
I did want to review, so while I'm still recording,
let me do that.
Yeah, let me share one more time.
Yeah. You will have on... Whoops, what happened to my
red pen here? There we go. You will have
your
S, which is distance between
shield
and wall, and you will have wall thickness on
this side.
And it will look something like this.
How high you go up will be dependent on your assumptions, but
you should be roughly going from zero to either
25 or 30, I think I specified it,
centimeters.
And it should have a general trend like that.
Okay. Got you. Thank you.
Okay. Thanks for pointing that out.
Yeah. So we'll see you next time.
Have a good night.
Good night.